Guide to the Civil Service Technical Guild Photograph Collection PHOTOS 012
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Civil Service Technical Guild Photographs
1922-1987, (Bulk 1960s-1970s)
1960-1979
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Civil Service Technical Guild
PHOTOS 012
2.25 Linear Feet
The Civil Service Technical Guild, established in 1937 to represent engineers and architects employed by the City of New York; was founded by three engineers: Henry F. Cunningham, William F. Elliot, and George Ellenoff. In 1956 it merged with American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees, District 37, as that organization's Local 375. By the 1960s the Guild had won the right of collective bargaining and over the years won for its members improved salaries, medical and dental benefits, Social Security and long-term disability insurance. Spanning the years 1922 to 1980, the collection of ca. 400 black and white photographs represents every aspect of the Guild's existence and activities. Most are of routine gatherings such as banquets and meetings, and these include portraits and posed group photographs with Guild presidents Louis Albano, Philip Brueck, Joseph Collins, Richard Izzo, and Alexander Lurkis,, but a few are less formal and provide more information on the material culture and the social lives of the early union members. In addition, some photographs document subway construction at several different time periods and different locations. Some of the photographers/photographic studios whose work is included in this collection are: John Adams Davis; Drunker, Hilbert Co.; Roland Harvey; Photographic Unit of the New York City Transit Authority; Sam Reiss; A.G. Schoenfeld; Ed Sheenan; Vincent Stibler; and Whitestone Photos.
(ca. 400 items); 3x5, 5x7,8x10; b&w
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Photographs in this collection were separated from the Civil Service Technical Guild Records WAG.024, and established as their own collection, the Civil Service Technical Guild Photographs PHOTOS.011. The accession number associated with these materials is 1984.007. Over the years, there have been a number of additions made to this collection. The accession numbers associated with this collection are NPA.2004.069, NPA.2004.076, NPA.2004.086, NPA.2005.031, NPA.2006.022, NPA.2006.082, 2011.092, and NPA.2005.031.
Arrangement
Arrangement is topical within series, with the exception of Series VI, which is arranged chronologically.
Organized into 8 series:
Missing Title
I. Activities, Unofficial
II. Activities, Official
III. Administrative
IV. Construction
V. Oversize
VI. Chronological
VII. Negatives and Contact Sheets
VIII. Unprocessed
Historical/Biographical Note
The Civil Service Technical Guild was established in 1937 to represent engineers and architects employed by the City of New York. It began as Council 6 of the Civil Service Forum by three engineers, Henry F. Cunningham, William F. Elliot, and George Ellenoff. The first activity of the organization was a protest against the contracting out of public works by the City to private firms. The union mobilized 300 engineers who went to the state capitol to lobby for the passage of the Buckley Law, which proposed repealing from the New York City charter a provision which actually required contracting out of large projects. After the passage of the Buckley Law, the Guild's membership increased by approximately 2,000 new members, representing 25 city departments (adding chemists and technical inspectors, among others).
In 1948 the Guild disaffiliated from the Civil Service Forum and was independent until 1951 when it merged with the Government and Civic Employees Organizing Committee (GCEOC) of the CIO, and finally with the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees, District 37 after the AFL-CIO merger in 1956. One of the key figures in the founding of the Guild was Philip Brueck, who was elected its President in 1938 and held that post for almost twenty years. Building upon the passage of the Buckley Law, Brueck's political strategy for the Guild was to lobby for legislation rather than to use strikes. By the 1960s the Guild had won the right of collective bargaining and over the years won for its members improved salaries, medical and dental benefits, Social Security and long-term disability insurance.
Provenance
The records of the Civil Service Technical Guild were assembled by the union in cooperation with the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, NYU during an oral history project initiated in 1984 in preparation for the Guild`s fiftieth anniversary. In the absence of a body of official union records, items were donated from the private collections of the following officers and members: Philip Brueck, President 1938-1955, Alexander Lurkis, President 1956-1958, Bill Goldsborough, William Malloy, Joseph Collins, President 1958-1972, Louis Albano, President 1981-1998, David Jacobson, James Parker, Eleanor Eastman, David Sedacca, and Harold Haldorsen.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Records of the American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District Council 37, Local 375, Civil Service Technical Guild (Wagner 24).
Scope and Content Note
This collection of black and white photographs spans the years 1922 to 1980 and represents every aspect of the Guild's existence and activities. It is organized into seven series, and within the series, mostly by subject. The subjects include: dinners, meetings, elections, demonstrations, rallies, subway construction, portraits, and hearings. In some cases photographs were not entirely identified or dated.
Some of the most interesting photographs in the collection are those that show subway construction at several different time periods and many different locations, including an album completed by the Transit Commission in 1922 showing subway construction to Queens.
While most of the photographs are of routine gatherings such as banquets and meetings, many in formal poses, a few images are less formal and provide more information on the material culture and the social lives of the early union members. These include the staff of the Brooklyn Borough President's office at work and at play (at the beach) and lively snapshots of CSTG'ers alternately posing and clowning outdoors at early conventions. Also pictured, in portraits and group photographs are Civil Service Technical Guild presidents, including Louis Albano, Philip Brueck, Joseph Collins, Richard Izzo, and Alexander Lurkis.
Some of the photographers/photographic studios whose work is included in this collection are: John Adams Davis; Drunker, Hilbert Co.; Roland Harvey; Photographic Unit of the New York City Transit Authority; Sam Reiss; A.G. Schoenfeld; Ed Sheenan; Vincent Stibler; and Whitestone Photos.
Labor union meetings |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.; Civil engineers |z New York (State) |z New York |v Portraits.; Public works |x Law and legislation |z New York (State) |z New York.; Architects |z New York (State) |z New York |v Portraits.; White collar workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Negatives (photographic); Demonstrations |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.; Collective bargaining |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) |x Officials and employees |v Portraits.; Black-and-white photographs.; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.). Government and Civic Employees Organizing Committee; Izzo, Richard. -- |v Portraits; Lurkis, Alexander. -- |v Portraits; Davis, John Adams.; AFSCME. District Council 37 (New York, N.Y.); Harvey, Roland.; Reiss, Sam; Schoenfeld, A.G.; Sheenan, Ed.; Civil Service Forum (New York, N.Y.); Stibler, Vincent.; Albano, Louis. -- |v Portraits; Brueck, Philip -- |v Portraits; Civil Service Technical Guild; Whitestone Photos; Collins, Joseph. -- |v Portraits; New York City Transit Authority. Photographic Unit
- Series I: Activities
  - Anniversary, 25th, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anniversary, 40th, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brueck, Phil - Misc. dinners after retirement, 1963-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brueck, Phil - Retirement Dinner, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - City Hall Outing, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Collins, Joe. - Retirement Dinner, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dinner, 1940s-1949, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dinners, 1950 - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dinners, 1960 - 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dinners, 1970 - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Issacs, Helen - Retirement Party, Dinner, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Samowitz, Charles - Retirement Party, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Zuckerman - Retirement Party, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Staff of the (Brooklyn) Borough President's office--1930s- 1940s, ca.1930-1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series II: Activities, Official
  - AFL-CIO - State Convention, 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - AFSCME Meeting with Ted Kennedy, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Agency Shop Bill Signing, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Awards and Presentations – 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Beame, Mayor - Endorsement of 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Buckley, Bill, 0 (Box 1, Folder 19.1)
  - Carey, Governor - Endorsement of 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Carter, President - Meeting with 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - City Council, Presentation to 1945 – 1946, 1950s, 1945-1946, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Civil Service Association Convention 1939,40,42,46,47, 1939-1940, 1942, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - CPM Class 1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Demonstrations--1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Education—1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Election Meetings--1979 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Financial Control Board--1979 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Guild Chemist Seminar--1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Hearings, 1945-1980 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Hospital Rally--1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Housing Unit Contract, Signing of 1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Installations, 1952 - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Low Jones Education Commission--1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Meetings--1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Meetings, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Meeting, 1970-1978 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Meetings--1980 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Official Signings--1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Project Coordinator - Prep Course, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - School Board--1970 - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Tamiment/Wagner Presentation--1984 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Trips--1967 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Women's Division--1950s, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Exhibit materials, anniversary celebration, 1980s (Box Shared Tamiment 005, Folder 13)
- Series III: Administrative
  - Brueck, Phil – Portraits--1920s- 1970s, 1920-1979 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Collins, Joe--1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Freidland, Harvey, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - General Service Lab, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Guild Insigni—n.d., 0 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Izzo, Richard C., 1962-1979 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Miscellaneous Group Shots (at unidentified gatherings), 1939-1987 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Office Photographs--1940s-1967, 1940-1967 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Portraits, Non-Guild Staff, 1930-1980 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Staff Photographs, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Union Officers-- 1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Series IV: Construction
  - Work Photographs--Subways (album), 1929 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Flood Control Gates, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Power Plant Model, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Subway Expansion - 6th Avenue & 13th Street, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Photographs shot for the Transit Commission of New York City, showing construction of the Rapid Transit Subway and Elevated Lines of New York City, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Photographs shot for the Transit Commission of New York City, showing construction of the Rapid Transit Subway and Elevated Lines of New York City, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Tunnel Construction, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - City public works designed or worked on by CSTG members, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
- Series V: Oversize
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains panoramic photos from banquets, and from the CSTG Women's Division (including exhibit: "Global Women in Non-Traditional Jobs").
  - Oversize Photographs (Flat-file 7, Drawer 14)
  - Testimonial Dinners and Luncheon Held for Harry Jolles, John Daly, William Daly, and Colonel S. H. Bingham on the Occasions of their Retirement from the New York City Transit Authority, circa 1960 (Oversize Box XOS 1)
  - Third Annual Exhibition of CSTG, Local 375 Women's Organizing Committee: "Global Women in Non-Traditional Jobs", 1989 (Box 8, Folder 1-8)
- Series VI: Chronological
  - 1950s, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - 1950s?, [1950-1959] (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - 1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - 1960s?, [1960-1969] (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - 1970s?, [1970-1979] (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - 1980s?, [1980-1989] (Box 3, Folder 71)
- Series VII: Negatives and Contact Sheets
  - Contact sheets—Late 1970s-1980s, 1970-1989 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Negatives--Late 1970s-1980s, 1970-1989 (Box 3, Folder 73)
- Series VIII: Unprocessed
  - Testimonial dinners, conventions, worksite photos, 1937-1980 (Box Shared Tamiment 014, Folder 3)
  - Dinners, 1952-1956 (Box Shared Tamiment 014, Folder 4)
  - Women's Exhibit, 1987 (Box Shared Tamiment 011, Folder 3-4)